all right
[Music]
yoga is practiced by millions of
Americans and is often recommended as
therapy for a variety of medical
conditions but does it work and for what
in my last video I talked about how yoga
practitioners tend to report better
health status but they also tend to be
wealthier and confounding factors like
that make it hard to draw claims about
yoga efficacy for example when
population Studies have taken factors
like education or income into account
the yoga effects often evaporate you
can't really tell if something's good or
bad until you put it to the test
unfortunately only about a quarter of
the published studies examining the
effects of yoga on health or well-being
outcomes were randomized controlled
trials and of those half compared yoga
to basically just doing nothing in that
case if you find benefit you don't know
if it's the yoga itself or whether any
kind of exercise would have achieved the
same or even better effect now look any
kind of physical activity is good but is
there more to yoga than exercise for
example any kind of exercise whether low
intensity such as yoga or high intensity
such as aerobics may help with menstrual
pain compared to not doing anything in
studies on alcoholics aerobic exercise
alleviated depression and anxiety
symptoms more than yoga presumably just
because the greater exercise intensity
typical yoga is probably best described
as a light intensity physical activity
for example here's the metabolic
equivalence of some typical yoga poses
the average may be two or three compare
that to walking at a typical speed which
is about three so in general walking
Burns about as many calories as yoga and
brisk walking would burn even more
there's all sorts of crazy claims about
how so-called Hot Yoga expends up to
like a thousand calories but no you burn
about the same calories at room
temperature so 90 minutes would just be
more like 300 calories but isn't yoga so
much more than just a workout let's see
how the data pans out
multiple sclerosis for example we know
that exercise can be beneficial in many
health conditions including neurological
disorders and it may not be surprising
that yoga which involves a series of
poses postures movements and breathing
patterns that could improve balance
muscle strength and flexibility should
be found beneficial to patients with say
multiple sclerosis let's see if that's
actually true no benefit for overall
quality of life or physical quality of
life or psychological quality of life
also no benefit for sexual function or
cognitive function and this was all
comparing yoga to doing nothing a
similar failure to find much improvement
in quality of life for people living
with chronic diseases in general was
noted with only one in seven trials
finding a clinically significant benefit
researchers did find yoga helped fatigue
in patients with MS but not any better
than regular exercise same with chronic
low back pain yoga might decrease pain
and improve function compared to not
really doing anything but had the same
effect on pain and disabilities any
other exercise or physical therapy so if
you like yoga and want to make that your
exercise of choice voice great but it
doesn't appear to have any unique
benefits for back pain same with
insomnia Yoga Works compared to nothing
but not too Physically Active controls
and for cancer patients mostly breast
cancer patients walking was found to be
more effective than yoga and improving
sleep for markers of systemic
inflammation and breast cancer survivors
six months of yoga at a similar effect
as six months of non-yoga exercise same
with cancer-related fatigue and quality
of life for women with breast cancer
better than nothing but no better than
other types of physical activity finally
for breast cancer survivors the
effectiveness of yoga interventions and
breast cancer related lymphedema and
abnormal accumulation of fluid for which
there's no effective treatment and
adding yoga does not seem to help
there are some conditions for which yoga
really does appear to pull ahead of the
pack though for example chronic
non-specific neck pain based on 10
randomized control trials Not only was
yoga better for neck pain than control
groups in general which included doing
nothing yoga also seemed to beat out
active controls other types of exercises
the authors tentatively conclude that
yoga can relieve neck pain intensity
improve pain related disability increase
range of motion improve quality of life
and boost mood among neck pain sufferers
foreign